So for lists, I included a very, very handy list cheat sheet in this chapter where it talks about the use.
I show you how to create lists. I show you search methods, search speeds.
So searching for an item in a list in Python is actually quite slow because you have to check each value in it and some common methods.
So let's look at lists in practice.
You can declare lists two different ways. One is with these square brackets, square bracket notation, which is how you will commonly see lists being declared.
You can also declare them, oh, here this is come back to bite me. You can also declare lists by calling the constructor.
I got this type error, stir object is not colourful. That's because I declared a variable name to list earlier on in this program and I forgot about it.
So I'm going to exit my repal and restart it.
Weird. It looks like start repal is just broken in my VS code.
So I'm just going to start at the normal way because I have my virtual environment activated here. I can just type Python or we'll bring up the right thing.
So list can be declared with square bracket notation. They can also be declared by calling back constructor.
You're more likely to see this notation. You'll only really need to, you'll only really spot this when you're converting between different types.
And again, we can verify that type right there.
Lists have values that are separated by commas.
And in order to close off the list, you'll have to put that closing square bracket. If you forget it, especially in the repal, it's just going to do that.
And it means that Python is waiting for input. It's waiting for you to close that list. So as soon as you enter that closing square bracket that it expects and you press enter that will.
That will knock you out of that continuation.
And let's take a look at names. We'll see here that we have a few values.
Some methods that let you act on sequences like this. One that you'll see all the time is called Len. And that means give me the length of this sequence.
You can also access things in lists by index. So Python, like most programming languages is zero indexed.
I wanted the first name in this list of names. I would ask for name zero names one names two. I have three items in my list.
What error am I going to see when I ask for names at index three?
Yeah, so I'm going to see index error list index out of range.
And that's because there is no item at the third position.
I wanted to update an item in a list. And you can update an item in a list because a list is mutable, meaning that a list can be changed. You can do that with a zero with the index.
So now if I look at my list of names, I'll see Mark, Max and Jane.
You might notice that in Python, all of the items in the list don't have to be declared on the same line. So you might notice this more when you are working with long strings or large data types.
So I can declare a list like this and have the opening bracket and then the dot dot dot dot on the rebel means it's expecting more input. So I can just separate these line by line.
You'll notice here that trailing commas on like JSON are allowed. And in fact, in Python, I would say they're encouraged because they really help with diffs and version control.
So I tend to always include the trailing comma in my list definitions.
Let's declare some lottery numbers.
And let me fix that.
Put an equal sign.
So now I have a list of lottery numbers. If I wanted to sort these temporarily, I could call sorted on them.
You'll see here, though, that my original list has not changed.
Also, call sorted with reverse.
As an argument.
And this will take the sort and then reverse it. Again, though, this list has not changed.
I did want to sort in a place. I would have to call a method on the list called dot sort.
Now, if I take a look at my lottery numbers, variable, you'll see that it has in fact changed.
So the difference here is that this sorted is a built in and calling dot sort. I called dot sort on the variable itself.
And that's what allowed it to be changed in place.
Again, if you were curious about what methods are available in list, you can always call
DUR on list and then call help on any one of these by saying help, let's say list dot count.
And that will print out what the value or what this method does as well as what arguments it expects.
If you wanted to add items to a list, you can call the append method on it.
And pass in the new value.
And that will in fact change the list.
You can also insert items into a list by passing in an index.
I'm going to say index zero. So insert it at the beginning of the list.
Oops.
That insert.
And then if I take a look at that, remember zero is the position and 55 is the value that I'm inserting.
We'll see that it was inserted at the beginning of the list.
Is there any equivalent to an insert that doesn't mutate the list?
You could concatenate the list with a different one.
And that would return a new list. So for example.
Let's say a list of with the number one and three.
This will append create it will create a new list with these values appended.
But the original list will not in fact be changed.
If you wanted to see if an item was in a list, you would use the in keyword.
And this will either return true if the item is in the list or false if it's not.